本小組。
多謝主席。
然而，此框架缺乏對受壓迫羣體學生所面臨的掙扎的真確理解。
inclusive measures, for example, mother tongue policy was implemented by education bureau in 1998, putting EM students at a disadvantage.
政府部門和 bureaus are adopted. Not all government departments and bureaus are covered. So my first suggestion is that the scope should be expanded to cover all public authorities.
Language is a race-related characteristic. EDB has not systematically addressed this issue up till 2014, when CSL Chinese as a second language framework and support measures to non-Chinese speaking students in learning Chinese was implemented.
考慮少數民族需求將會成為一個後thought，而不是政策制定過程中的核心部分。一個主要原因是公營機構缺乏雄心和承諾，是因為該指南對他們施加了很少或沒有責任。
咧我或者都誒為咗慳時間咧，局長或者你都留翻之後先再講咧，好嘛？噉我哋馬上可以去由我哋嘅誒公眾人士發言咧。噉我哋誒首先有請就係誒Miss Pail Biswas of the Society for Cultural Integration，please go ahead please。
都馬上開翻先啦。噉啊誒，首先我必須係對誒誒，在座工作人員道歉，因為我哋之前嗰節咧係長咗，同埋有啲答案答案，可能你之前係睇到個電視熒光幕咧，可能都知道下啲答案。希望大家唔好介意，我哋而家今日係好多官員出席咧，好多議員出席嘅。噉我哋爭取時間咧，馬上呢一節。
Hello everyone. The admin guidelines mention that public authorities should adopt the good practices of considering the promotion of racial equality as an integral dimension in the formulation of policies, implementation and review of relevant policies and measures. So why is it that only 23?
措施listed out by respective public authorities are at best remedial and piecemeal. Almost all relevant public authorities mention providing interpretation services and leaflets in multiple languages, but shy away from making racially inclusive policies and reviewing the existing less.
There is a lack of stage learning objectives, teaching materials and professional resources and guidance on textbooks whose mother tongue is not Chinese. Developing teaching materials and textbooks should be the responsibility of the government and education bureau. There is no reporting mechanism in place under the guidelines where.
ethnic minorities receive poorer services from relevant public authorities. So, for example, if I go to social welfare department and they don't arrange interpretation services, or am I discriminated against? Where can I make a complaint? Ethnic minority service users may register a complaint with public authorities providing the service, but the feedback.
get buried or lost within the authority, since any intentional or unintentional non-compliance does not result in any consequences such as punishment or loss of reputation for the authority, the guidelines can hardly generate any culture or attitude change in public authorities. As such.
CMAB did not do something for the guidelines, but just put it as a checklist. The CMAB leaves the implementation of these guidelines and development of measures to the discretion of individual public authorities. The CMAB should be the bureau to implement the guidelines, ensure compliance and penalise.
非 compliance，如果一個公共 Authority under delivers it measures。 Thank you so much。 Thank you, Mrs. Woods。 我之前我哋而家就啲委員喺度在席嘅時候咧，我哋啊處理咗毛曼志議員嗰個動議先啦。我哋轉頭先再做翻我哋嘅公眾人士諮詢啦。咁或者秘書李鴿咪讀嗰個誒動議方面，我哋記錄在案。
誒。
第二年 undergraduate student studying global business at HKUST.
但係，非常容易，作為proficiency level，低至primary four。
你cannot be a doctor speaking your Chinese like a primary four student.
我 wanted a career in Hong Kong as a doctor, but to be a doctor, you need to be able to fulfil the Chinese requirement.
一啲嘅current remedial measures係讓ethnic minority students take GCSE Chinese to go to university.
我的右，要 choose 我 life's path was taken away from me， when the system chose not to teach me proper Chinese.
好，我哋馬上跟住翻翻嚟我哋嘅公眾諮詢嘅誒環節咧。誒，May I invite Mr. Data Data please?
今天我會講述整個產業因為政府的應試措施而被完全關閉，對少數民族學生，因為政府的應試措施而被關閉。
Based on today's Chinese education system for ethnic minorities, why don't we all go to kindergartens and tell ethnic minority children they will never become a doctor?
When I was going through primary and secondary school in Hong Kong, I was taught an easier level of Chinese. But when the time came to start a career, Chinese became a problem.
since the handover, Chinese language ability has become a must across Hong Kong society and even the government, but the education system has not caught up in these 20 years.
係，我諗誒都好好即係straightforward嘅一個同意啦。咁有冇在座有冇邊位係需要發言或者贊成反對？如果冇嘅話咧，我哋就當通過就可以啦，係嘛？因為呢個我相信都冇乜大嘅反意見嚇。
我 went into a good high school, studied hard and did well on my public exams and received so much support from my teachers. Yet my right to choose was taken away from me because of the system.
本小組委員會敦促政府盡早修訂條誒種族歧視條例，把政府職能及職權納入條例檢討中，彌補促進種族平等行政指引的不足，以助促進種族平等。
Hello everybody, my name is Siddhartha. I have lived in Hong Kong for 19 years with my family here and studied at an ethnic minority designated kindergarten and primary school. Then I had the good fortune to study at La Salle College for six years, where I studied and worked amongst the best Chinese students in Hong Kong. And today I'm a
它 raises the question.
ability to learn English language exists.
Why set a Chinese language requirement if it is not required for you to do your job?
Good evening, everyone. I'm Sahara, currently studying at the University of Hong Kong.
Not all doctors need to speak Chinese to all patients, as there are ethnic minority patients.
我的第二個建議其實開始於就業部門，以及它如何圍繞著非少數民族學生。
did the government do enough to ease the transition, especially in terms of CSL education?
多謝。多謝，Mr. Tato。我們現今邀請Mr. Harapathin Mohammed，請。
要幫助ethnic minorities in Hong Kong，我會建議政府可以從結構調整教育政策開始。
另一個 reason that is causing this issue is that all ethnic minority students are brought under the same umbrella.
The EDB should set a proper curriculum for ethnic minorities in Hong Kong to attain a certain level of proficiency, instead of simply relying on GCSE Chinese as a remedy.
and within the government itself, there is nobody who could properly deal with ethnic minorities properly, and therefore there is a need to understand that ethnic minorities have a right to choose their career in life.
今天我來到帶出光問題，出現於每間學校為族裔少數羣設計自己的中文課程，那會適合他們的中文族裔少數學生。
logically speaking，if 1% of the Hong Kong population is an ethnic minority，then we should permit at least a proportionate 1% of ethnic minorities into all working industries，both as a matter of equality and efficiency。
我們 want the same for our Chinese language curriculum, a standard that is shared among all born in Hong Kong ethnic minority students, unlike now in which some are fluent and yet some struggle due to different levels taught in school.
At present, the level of difficulty of Chinese standard varies from school to school designated for ethnic minorities. We want consistency in the level and standard, just like English language standards are kept the same throughout all schools in Hong Kong, even the variations in the teaching materials and all students.
begin from kindergarten.
雖然我係巴基斯坦人。
大家好，我叫阿B白。
我都係香港人，好似你哋噉樣。
但我都係香港土生土長，好似你哋噉樣。
我哋都係普通嘅中小學讀中文，好似你哋噉樣。
我哋都想喺香港發展，香港做嘢，好似你哋噉樣。
Thank you, Miss Mohamed. We now have Miss Habiba Aslamy, please.
born in Hong Kong students can do more, but they have been taught way less due to the current system.
Having attained at least level three equivalent results, we would be able to transit to employments for the education and integration.
我哋想努力學好中文，我哋希望香港政府會繼續支持我哋進步中文，能夠幫我哋融融入香港社會。唔該。
One group is the ones that are born in Hong Kong, and the other group is the newcomers to Hong Kong. We should be taught with two separate curriculums in regards to Chinese language.
born in Hong Kong ethnic minority students are capable of learning much much advanced level of Chinese than what they have been taught in the decade that have passed, due to schools catering the needs of newcomers together with the born in Hong Kong ethnic minorities.
Apparently, EDB lacks understanding of the diverse learning needs and backgrounds of ethnic minority students. The system is not adequate enough for us to learn Chinese language. There should be a clear division among ethnic minority students when it comes to designing of the Chinese language curriculum itself.
newcomers should be given the opportunity to do GCSE exams, but born in Hong Kong EM students should be given a separate new curriculum which will be equivalent to at least three level three of local DSE curriculum for the students of decade to come, and it ought to be designed with scrupulousness.
APLC is attempting to do this. However, it is done externally from the school. This duty has been shifted to outside institutes. While local DSE curriculum would be too difficult for us, the GCE is too easy for locally born students. We want to be proficient in speaking, reading and writing Chinese, and this training ought to be.
第三ly。
雖然。
首先。
第一個問題係邊度咧？
所以今日咧，我就想。
第二，來，學校。
講個分定。
個問題就係我哋冇資助讀中文。
個資助係邊度利用嘅？喺邊方面利用咗？
例如，我 brother 去去到一個本地小學，要學中文。
係點樣可以知道？我哋會點知道同埋應該要點誒處理嘅？
The schools may not be aware that there is such funding available for the students to learn Chinese.
他非常興奮和熱情地學習中文。他非常興奮，然而，他的興奮不長久。
They do not provide support to students who want to learn Chinese, even if they are just one or two ethnic minorities studying Chinese.
政府教育局有安排資助畀啲中小學，為咗我哋小小歲族裔嘅學生讀中文，但係我哋唔知道。
now there is funding, but the schools are not applying for it because they do not want to go through the administrative work just for one or two students in the local secondary or primary schools.
啲學校。
我們會想，要。
Selma Saka Aslam， please.
due to no support from school or teachers.
and HKDSE Chinese, which is not taken by a majority of us.
但但他係，他係一個非中文講嘅學生，他係perfectly fine。
Hello everyone. I'm Salma. I'm born and raised in Hong Kong, and currently I'm a student at HKUST.
I can speak fluent Cantonese. I'm looking forward to applying to civil service jobs upon graduation.
因為沒有支援，沒有支援學中文。相反，他被當作SEN特殊教育需要學生。
And today, he has no motivation to study at all. His his motivation or passion to study has died just because of that experience. Therefore,
not only did he do poorly in his Chinese subject, but also other subjects were affected because they were taught in Chinese medium, such as mathematics, general studies, etc.
then how can people like me who are born and raised in Hong Kong climb up the social ladder if constraints such as Chinese language entry requirements become a barrier?
request the EDB to monitor to have this monitoring mechanism, which you do have. However, we would like to have transparency, accountability to the public. We would like to have
但問題是，under the current entry requirements for government jobs, for example in the Customs and Excise Department, the language proficiency requirement is level two above in Chinese in HKDSE, which should be met.
要有財務報告，向公眾，特別是EMST學生和家長，報告如何使用撥款。我們希望學校鼓勵我們學習更多中文，並支持我們學習中文。謝謝。謝謝，Ms. Azman。接下來，我們有Ms.
However, alternative qualification for Chinese language proficiency, which is accepted for admission into university for non-Chinese applicants, such as GCE A-level Chinese language, is not considered for admission purposes for civil service. There is CREUs of Chinese, which is too difficult.
多謝主席。
There are obstacles on access to education.
佢哋係讀緊中一嘅中一。
多謝。我們現在有丹尼洛·安德烈，請。
Route for non-Chinese potentials to gain entry into civil service.
Right now, there are no government statistics on on the hiring practices of the ethnic minorities.
We embrace the early Chinese education for our children, so they could integrate socially into Hong Kong.
然而，未來我的孩子和 rest of ethnic minority students is still uncertain.
Even if they perform well, they're just stuck into their own positions. That's all what I have to say. Thank you.
其他國家，如新加坡，有豐富多樣的人民在政府工作，為什麼香港不能從這些例子中學習？
They studied in a Chinese medium school from kindergarten to primary. They can speak now fluent Cantonese, read and write elementary Chinese.
The guidelines by CMAB state that it emphasises on providing equal services on all levels. Are they really equal?
my name is Daniel Reyes. I am a Filipino working as researcher and teaching assistant at CTU. I am a father of two. My daughter is P six and my son is P three.
Most of the work documents are in English, and with the ability to speak Cantonese fluently, I believe reading and writing Chinese should not be placed too much importance. But definitely, while working, it should be improved.
我見到自己為政府工作，和貢獻香港，和希望中文語言入學要求放寬，以至於例如中一中文語言級別B或以上可以考慮，或換句話説，政府可以再放寬另一個要求。
所以，如果例如，如果 Chinese language requirements are relaxed，什麼會是政府採取的措施，確保民族少數羣體得到提升，根據他們的優點？因為例如，警察社區聯繫官員不能升職，因為他們。
我係sure。
like taught in Chinese。
因為佢低平均分。
在我觀點，呢個政策矛盾。
教育 bureau is aware of its bunding system.
它 disappoints parents like us who embrace early Chinese education.
secondary schools follows this bundling system in admission process.
我受 shock to learn the assessment criteria for students applying for admission.
到政府嘅idea of early Chinese education as a route for social integration。
Our problem now is she might not get an offer of admission from an English medium school.
another school counts the students' band thirty percent of their overall criteria.
我 take my daughter as an example. She got straight A's in English, but low marks for scores rests.
When I submitted her application to a secondary school, I was told by a staff they would only accept students with B grades.
The allocated band to a student is used as basis by secondary schools in their offer of admission, as well as by the EDB in central allocation.
my eldest is entering into secondary one in September this year. Since December last year, I have applied for her admission to five secondary schools.
How can parents be encouraged to send their children to Chinese medium schools early, if their chance to get a place in secondary school is very low?
Thank you.
這政策必須被全面審視。
我係Concerned that the EDB's report for today's public hearing on this never addressed this issue.
在 my view， this policy affects ethnic minority students' equal access to education and their future， including that of my children.
我 call on the ADB as well as Equal Opportunities Commission to look into the implications of bunding system to ethnic minority students.
咁誒亦都應該係直上交畀大家㗎啦，或者誒請我容許誒秘書從事咧就誒就兩個誒動議咧，但係誒先處理咗誒張超雄嘅動議先嚇。
thank you, Mr. Andrew。誒，跟住我哋有請醫護行者嘅劉海寧小姐，唔該。多謝主席。誒，首先想多謝各位議員留到最後去誒聽埋我哋嘅分享啦。咁頭先上個節其實都已經討論咗好多唔同嘅議題，噉我哋儘量唔重複，咁反而係就住個別議題，我哋想再深入啲跟進少少嘅。咁有三個方面，第一。
一個方面係關於誒醫管局嘅義務翻譯噉樣，我哋機構比較關注係少數在尋求醫療服務嘅情況啦。噉我哋都數字上睇到，其實醫管局好好嘅，的確係一年係可以做到一萬嘅人次嘅翻譯服務。咁其實相對其他公營機構，的確係值得讚賞。咁但係我哋都想再誒去深入帶出誒普通科目。
門診G.O.P.C個問題咧，由我哋上年大概呢個時間去到今年，其實都未處理到。我哋其實仍然係收到一啲個案，係佢想喺G.O.P.C普通科門診嗰度去得到翻譯服務，但係誒係冇法冇辦法得到服務。而呢一個問題咧，我哋想再深入啲去傾，其實唔係淨係講緊能唔能夠使用服務。
誒特首喺佢嘅施政報告入邊有講到基層醫療嘅重要性啦。其實普通科門診作為公營系統基層醫療嘅把關，如果我哋少數族裔嘅病人其實用唔到呢個服務咧，好多時我哋睇到嘅係佢哋個病情會等到惡化，或者真係被逼要去到急症室先至去睇醫生，而呢一個其實係影響緊佢哋係。
延遲咗病情，咁所以講緊個服務個翻譯服務唔係淨係佢講唔講到嘢，而其實其實係會影響個身體嘅狀況嘅。咁第二個議題係關於誒去收集數據啦。咁上一節都有好多立法會議員啦，或者去誒公眾朋友都有提到呢一點。噉就住收服誒收一啲數據，其實除
除咗係做翻一啲即係measure嘅implementation之外咧，喺例如喺醫療上，其實好重要嘅係去做個needs assessment嘅。我哋上一年都有提到，其實我哋自己前線睇到，佢最簡單BMI，巴基斯坦婦女同埋我哋嘅華裔婦女，其實嗰個obesity rate個黐肥嗰個率其實已經爭好遠。其實我。
係需要呢一啲數據先至能夠做到服務規劃噉，所以數據嘅重要性係係有好多個方面嘅。咁另一個例子誒，上一節誒，我哋有個朋友都有提到Ontario嘅例子啦。噉我哋另一個上課嘅例子係紐西蘭。咁紐西蘭政府佢好好嘅，佢出咗個protocol咧，正正就係話喺健康health同埋係social。
究竟唔同嘅公營服務提供者可以透過誒，即係有啲乜嘢protocol係淨係收集數嘅啫？即係除咗CMAB guideline之外，我哋有個建議就係會唔會可以請評議會或者自己CMAB，甚至乎其他嘅機構去定立一個淨係關於收集數據嘅guideline，噉就可以令到個別嘅服務提供者，例如醫管局啦，就唔會有。
個擔心話：，我會唔會可能佢收集數據係造成歧視咧？咁呢個一個建議。咁最後一個方面咧，就係關於個跟進。噉我哋都好感激誒立法會可以延延續呢個委員會多一年啦。咁但係我哋其實自己開始都諗緊過多幾個月之後，誒其實好可能都未變可以再延續一年。咁究竟我哋會上討？
嗯。
將誒。
住啦，咁咁點啊？
政府咧做啲研究咧，佢就揀咗。
必須以消除歧視或促進種族平等為目的。
其中九項，咁其實總共有七十幾項嘅，平機會再將佢縮減為廿幾項係緊急嘅。
跟住係，誒，跟住處理小嘉張議員嘅動議啊，唔該。政府經常以避免種族歧視為理由，拒絕收集與少數族裔服務使用者。
啊誒係對唔住，或者我哋我睇唔到在席上有有邊一反對聲音啦。咁因為我哋都人數相對比較少，我哋誒如果冇反對嘅話，我哋就當通過咗呢個動議，就就處理下一個動議好嘛。
但係而家我哋好似講到佢已經拒絕咗，咁以後就你都認可咗佢係拒拒絕咗，咪以後唔使傾。我好擔心。是否需要修正下你嘅動議，定還是你覺得係？主席係噉，即係評議會就提提咗呢個建議啦。
一步進一步嘅需要處理嘅話，我哋都當通過咗啦，好嘛，因為簡單啲係。阿毛孟正宇，你係咪想入去講呢個？我係係係好擔心嘅。誒誒，張超雄嗰個提誒誒嗰個motion咧，佢喺度話政府係拒絕咗誒。
論罪嘅點樣去跟進咧，會唔會係例如我哋關注嘅醫療議題，係咪翻翻去衞生事務委員會個panel，定係會唔會其實整體上係C M A B跟進咁？都希望我哋開始一齊去傾咯。多謝主席。好唔該，謝劉小姐。誒喺原定法定時間終結前咧，或者容許我哋處理咗。剛才另外兩位同事咧，就有兩個分別有兩個誒動議嘅。
讀圖好嗎？因為為咗公眾起見，我想讀，即係比較長少少嘅嚇。雖然香港有種族歧視條例及促進種族平等行政指引，但條例並不應用於政府平等機會委員會要求及早修例，將政府納入法例規管範圍。
但政府卻拒絕此建議。指引雖然訂立了，卻完全沒有監察，令香港少數族裔在使用公共服務時，包括教育、房屋、醫療、就業及社福等，受到不平等對待。本小組委員會促請政府立即進行修。
並成立一高層次少數族裔事務委員會，從少數族裔的角度監察政府政策、公共服務法例及資源分配，確保少數族裔得到平等機會及免於受到歧視。好，跟住我哋有趙家津議員嘅一個動議。
相的相關數據，但事實上不少國家已清楚列明收集數據反而是積極杜絕種族歧視的有效手段。本委員會促請政府訂立收集資料指引，確保收集及使用相關種族資料時。
歧視條例入面話有關政府嘅嗰啲誒powers and functions就誒即係唔好再exam咁嚇噉。佢話你誒，但政府卻拒絕此建議。我我嘅印象就政府未曾拒絕，喂都唔夠膽拒絕嘅。問咗佢，佢都話冇拒。
easily and feel welcome.
部處嘅張木欣先生，唔該。多謝主席。
再見啦！We now invite Mr. the one faithful alum of the DAB, please.
所以， people can segregate into different places or allow some of the playground for one-time congregation during Eid. Due to need of places, some religious groups renting flats in some buildings for prayers, which does not have adequate facilities.
咁呢個都係其中一個緊急，同埋應該盡快做。政府咧就從來都冇話佢唔做，不過佢就係唔做。咁所以對我嚟講咧，即係佢研究完之後，佢話做咗九項，但係就冇包呢項。佢誒其他嘅建議咧，政府就話我哋研究。
有部時間表咧冇噉，所以對我嚟講咧，呢個等同拒絕噉，所以即係呢個我用嘅字眼啦。誒的而且確咧，由於我哋係即係臨時嘅動議咧，亦都時間上比較倉促咧。噉我或者如果係政府當局咧，就任何動議嘅內容嘅字眼需要澄清嘅話咧，因為本身唔係約束有約束性嘅動議啦，大家個意見表達啫噉。
我相信政當局可以處理好嘛。我哋都唔想就呢件事咧，係個係要一個就一個延長咗一個辯論，或者要再投票噉樣。噉啊，邵家津原嗰個動議咧，都大家剛才都誒聽過啦。如果冇乜在座嘅反對聲音嘅話咧，我哋就誒都當咗係處理咗啦。好嘛，我哋慢慢劃上翻返我哋今日嘅主題，主處理翻有關公眾人士嘅誒。
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. This is Dewan Sir Falalum. I am a former president of Bangladeshi Association and DAB ethnic minorities member. I mean committee member. So I'd like to give some points where government can look into and gives it will make things better for the ethnic minorities. Number one is.
There are not enough worship places for multiple religious groups. As an example, for the Muslim, the existing mosque cannot accommodate the people during Friday prayers and Eid prayers. Therefore, they do the prayers in different sessions, causing chaotic situations when entering and exiting within short span of time. The government should provide more spaces.
for the immigration purpose. So, like though it is understandable as to why the government has implemented visa requirements for some of the countries like Bangladesh, Nepal, Pakistan etc., it is becoming more difficult and inconvenient due to lengthy processing time for the real business visitors and family members of the resident to obtain visa. The government should arrange faster visa.
Processing for the frequent business visitors and close relatives of Hong Kong residents. Also, they should be provided multiple entry visas with longer validity, so it won't be a repetitive process. Plus, it will reduce the workload of the immigration officers. Your support, the government should encourage and support ethnic minorities.
For graduating after graduating to become entrepreneur, the Innovative and Technology Commission should provide sponsoring and help the ethnic minority by funding. They can then use their talents and skills to invent and expand businesses. Also, through more vocational training, the government should have widened the scope of using EM youths.
與多樣的才能，就業機會，政府應該繼續推動和前行政長官在政策演講中提到的，審視中國的要求，讓民族少數可以爭取一些公務員的就業機會。NGO和資金，政府正在撥款支持一些NGO，支援民族少數，但
決定，或者舉個例，醫療決定嘅時候咧，如果個意見同我哋相違背的話咧，對佢哋權益咧就得不到保障。
令個少數做業人士未能獲得平等機會使用公共服務咧，其中嘅最大嘅障礙咧，我哋相信都係同佢哋嘅言語障礙有關。
誒關注嘅民生議題及投票意向嘅研究喺當中，發現咧少數族裔嘅社羣咧，佢哋最關注嘅民生範疇嘅第三位咧，就係使用公共服務上面遇到困難。
好多政府部門咧喺佢哋嘅指引上面咧，都會話鼓勵自己內部嘅同事咧去用翻譯服務。噉，但係我哋見到嘅情況咧就未必真係完全係噉，因為我哋紙機構咧都有一個服務誒，融匯咧係提供少數嘅翻譯服務。噉我哋見到咧，其實個情況咧誒有一啲觀察係誒噉樣嘅。
As far as we know, almost all of them are not run by the ethnic minorities themselves. The government should instead provide direct funding to some of the ethnic minority associations or societies, which can directly help the ethnic minorities for easier event management, public housing, and social interaction. As part as part the statistics, EM families.
tend to have more members in a household and the poverty rate is also higher. So the government should prioritise the public housing accommodation. Otherwise, it is very challenging to survive in the high rent of Hong Kong. The government should encourage the public housing estate committees to welcome the ethnic minorities, include them in activities or events organised by them, thus they can integrate with them.
答案：，The government should have equipped more school to give better learning environment for EM students with special educational needs, and also for the aged people, to encourage them to go to the I mean home for aged. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Lam. 或者我哋將個時間延長到七點鐘先啦。嚇，我哋跟住再請香港基督教服務。
啊！促進種族平等行政指引咧，其中一個誒出發點咧，就係要讓少數族裔人士有平等機會獲得社會提供嘅資源同埋公共服務。不過，我哋睇翻現況咧，指引執行到而家咧情況仍然有好大嘅改進空間。好似上年，我哋機構同社聯進行咗一項叫做少數族裔。
另外，我哋機構咧上年亦都進行咗一項，名為咧少數族裔婦女家暴經驗及求助行為模式嘅研究。喺當中發現咧，有八成以上我哋嘅受訪嘅南亞裔嘅女被訪者咧，佢哋通常日常用嘅溝通嘅言語啦，同埋用嘅啊文字啦。
都係用佢哋嘅母語，並唔係英語，所以咧誒，我哋都同我哋誒現實經驗咧都近似咧，就係其實唔少少數族嘅人士咧係唔識英語，所以我哋覺得淨係提供英語嘅誒一啲嘅文字咧，其實對你未必有直接幫助。最直接幫助嘅方法就係提供誒。
一個使用誒翻譯服務，不過喺使用翻譯服務上面咧，其實好多政府部門作為服務提供者咧，都未如理想嘅。大家都聽過好多例子啦，服務提供者咧可能好多時咧都冇問過少數族裔嘅服務使用者需唔需要用翻譯服務，噉佢都會可能會因為方便咧就會邀。
要求少數族裔服務嘅使用者嘅朋友，譬如丈夫啦、誒親友啦，或者佢嘅小朋友咧，作為佢哋臨時嘅翻譯員。不過最重要嘅問題就係，如果呢呢啲少數族裔嘅服務使用者同佢哋呢啲嘅翻譯員喺一啲嘅意見上面係唔同、相違背嘅時候，做一啲重大。
誒，我哋舉個政府部門為例啦，社署啊。我哋誒誒社署撇除，可能佢哋都有一啲自己誒翻譯服務嘅供應商啦，或者係一啲誒誒其他翻譯服務啦。咁喺我哋嘅服務數字裏邊咧，以一五一六年一五年九月去到一六年九月嘅數字去睇咧，誒電話。
翻譯服務嘅使用量咧，誒係全年係二百三十三次，係佔全年嘅總用量咧係七個percent。呢個誒係包括部門係有F C P S U啦、I F S C啦，同埋S S F U嘅。而職場翻譯服務咧使用量咧係十四次，噉係全年不足兩個percent。咁誒，所以咧其實。
誒，關於單位嗰個安裝視像嗰個服服務使用咧，都係零㗎。咁所以咧，我哋建議咧就係誒促進種族平等行政指引咧，應該唔係一個參考或者指導性嘅政策文件，而係應該各部門咧係需要按指引咧制定相關嘅政策、執行指標、監測機制。另外咧，亦都要咧誒持續收集服務數。
據啦，定期諮詢少數罪服務事持份者嘅意見，優化配套。而各政府部門咧，亦都誒係要定期提供使用翻譯服務嘅數字，同埋服務使用誒服務少數罪業人士嘅數目，具透明度嘅交代機制咧，相信有助執行誒指引。另外，政制誒及內地事務局咧。
係。
《聯合國兒童權利公約》。
leaving behind the comfort of her home to escape conflicts and devastation in Egypt, the mother of three young children is seeking refuge in Hong Kong in search of safety and stability.
我們唔係來到這裡學， no， 我們來到這裡帶這些孩子到安全。我們找一個地方給他們，那係遠離傷害，那裡可以有未來給他們。
懷孕和哺乳婦女、單身婦女、 travelling alone and with children，和婦女， who suffered from sexual violence in trafficking， struggle with accessing justice and security.
如何，的guidelines， incentivise，different，departments，to，aspire，to，best，practice，and，higher，standards，of，implementation，to，ensure，that，we，comply，with，our，international，human，rights，obligations。Without，accountability，there，is，a，critical，gap，in，the，system。
多謝。Next we have Ms Fatma Kureish of the Refugee Union Hong Kong, please. Thank you, Chairman. I work and volunteer for the Refugee Union, so I'd first like to start with, in the words of a mother.
亦都需要加強公眾同埋少數族裔人士對呢個指引嘅認識。另外，都有責任咧設立機制咧去持續監察各政府部門嘅執行情況。多謝主席。張生誒，We now invite Miss Pooja Kapar, Centre for Comparative Public Law, Faculty of Law, University of Hong Kong, please. Thank you, Chairman. So, although the guidelines require the integration of an
質影響視角在於政策的制定和實施。公眾機構在應用指引時，未能充分展示如何做到。如何做到？如何做到
On grounds of race are present, they pertain almost singularly to eliminating language barriers by providing access to interpretation services. These measures do not address the systemic issues and inequities which render a system racially discriminatory and fundamentally inaccessible. Equality of access is not just about having the opportunity to be served by public
但要被服務在一個實質性、有意義的 manner。指南線已經短，粗魯地短於這些標準，期望由上位法規所規定。我們也知道，這個歧視條例本身是有限度的範圍。在這情況下，這些指南線則要承擔更重的責任，要嚴格和謹慎地確保。
that there is a process to understand, analyse and address the source of marginalisation of ethnic minorities in Hong Kong. This requires regular review, which is promoted by the guidelines. But again, it's unclear to me what the administration's understanding of review is. They simply say that their guidelines have now been extended to apply to 23 bureaus instead of 14.
但僅僅擴展數字上的範圍，並不必然能證明有實質性的改善。真正的問題是，這些指引本身有沒有對政策制定和服務中的亞裔社羣產生實際影響，改善他們的生活和基本權利？這就是根本問題。
the data on outcomes of review provided by the administration is limited to satisfaction level with interpretation services or training. Achieving substantive change in the elimination of racial discrimination or disadvantage requires more than just approval ratings for piecemeal remedial measures, which are really responding to a problem created by the very
system itself. Today's numerous deputations provide ample examples of the data demonstrating the systemic disadvantage experienced by ethnic minorities in Hong Kong. This serves as an ample report card on the value and worth of these guidelines in achieving the objectives that they have set out to. The administration has to recognise that where you have a problem.
which is of systemic proportions, the solution necessarily also is required to be systemic. There is no mandatory review or evaluation of policies or reporting requirements by the bureaus regarding the implementation of these guidelines or assessing their discriminatory impact. The lack of accountability or omission or oversight of the implementation of the guidelines limits any positive.
或 remedial impact that they may have, where racial inequality is systemically experienced and undermines the life prospects and potential for equal protection and enjoyment of human rights, there is no room for an honour system based on the discretionary benevolence of individual bureaus and departments. It behoves the administration to explain.
多謝，Miss Gracia。
Indeed，Hong Kong is not a signatory to the Refugee Convention.
necessities for refugee women and families that only increases their vulnerability.
誒，跟住我哋就請誒關注婦女性暴力協會嘅黃秀容女士，唔該。多謝主席。
幾點嘅即係調查，我哋都睇到有幾點，我哋值得去注意啦。咁希望咧喺即係呢一個種族平等行政指引去做review嘅時候都可以考慮啦。咁第一咧，我哋睇到咧，其實
嘅文化背景嘅獨特性咧，其實係誒重要嘅呢方面。咁然而咧，我哋都更加可以肯定，就係如果因為家報同埋聖報求助嘅時候咧，其實更加需要注意呢個翻譯嘅性別啦。
會喺一二年咧，其實開展咗呢一個少數族裔嘅女性嘅服務，提供咗一啲性暴力嘅支援服務同埋社區教育畀佢哋咧。我哋都睇到好多嘅問題啦，噉樣。咁其實喺舊年五月咧，我哋都進行咗一個有關香港少數族裔翻譯服務嘅研究。咁喺誒個研究入邊咧，我哋都。
serving as temporary hosts, but we should never forget that refugees are after all trying to live a normal life. And while they're here, why shouldn't Hong Kong facilitate access to and greater efficiency of its services to those who, for now, call Hong Kong their home? Thank you.
now we know half of the world's refugees are children under 18 years of age and around half of the total number of refugees are women or girls and I may be referencing from the UN General Assembly report but we also know that Hong Kong has also long signed off on the rights to education for refugee children and for those not familiar the Hong Kong government in 1994 signed the
但，lots of families we know can't afford to buy new school supplies every year in terms of education. Their children can't share equal time and opportunities with their classmates. The family of the woman who fled Egypt have called Hong Kong their home now. But why is it that they're weighed down by the school to make purchases of school uniform and materials that are not even subsidised?
The unwarranted pressure on women is also caused by the burden of footing the bill for special healthcare treatments, both physical and mental, both of which are also important and should be readily available. But we don't really find that in healthcare services. Refugee women's needs, priorities and voices are often missing from humanitarian welfare assistance designed to protect.
一些女性和兒童尋求庇護在香港是有權留在此處，即使在轉運，但大多數需要近十年才能獲得難民狀態批准，然後再移居第三國。所以，無法工作在第一個地方，讓他們只有依賴福利津貼和慈善。
what we've gathered in the refugee union from refugee women is that they're often the first responders in a crisis. Whether back at home, en route or in destination countries, they play a crucial role in caring for, sustaining and rebuilding their communities and families. But they can't do that if public services fail to secure basic
誒，香港嘅性暴力個案報案率都好低㗎啦。咁但係大部分性暴力嘅事件，我哋都知道係社會被隱藏嘅。咁但係至於少數族裔婦女，我哋知道咧，佢哋無論性暴咧或者家暴問題遇到嘅時候咧，大部分人都唔會報警嘅。而少數族裔嘅婦女咧，較於男性咧，其實佢哋嘅教育程度比較低啦。
啊啊！周樂行先生唔該。
甚至唔識英語啦，同埋咧係中文咧比例咧都係更加係唔識嘅，更加係低嘅。因此咧，佢哋根本無法接觸外界嘅資訊，甚至唔知道咧香港係有機構係為佢哋係提供社會服務嘅。咁再加上佢哋嘅羣眾嘅壓力啦，就算遇到佢哋暴有暴力嘅時候，佢哋都會選擇繼續啞忍嘅。咁所以我哋嘅。
喺我哋收到嘅一百七十份嘅有效問捲入邊咧，其實超過三分二嘅即係受訪者，佢哋認為咧，翻譯者嘅性別咧同埋服務使用者嘅相同係好重要嘅。咁甚至咧男性嘅受訪者，亦都係對於翻譯嘅性別表達係同樣嘅關注，顯示咧呢個唔係淨係女性嘅需求。咁而少數。
咁第二點咧，我哋睇到係真係需要咧，係提高少數族裔嘅一啲嘅翻譯嘅質素啦，同埋前線同工對文化同埋性別敏感嘅度嘅培訓嘅。咁其實喺家暴同埋性暴受害人，特別係少數族婦女咧，佢真係需要好大嘅勇氣去報警求助嘅。噉我哋即係一啲嘅。
即係依啲嘅婦女，我哋幫過佢哋。我哋睇到佢哋有文化啦、宗教啦、語言嘅障礙，佢哋去求助、去報警嘅時候，真係承受好大嘅壓力。咁甚至比本地婦女係更加沉重。咁如果咧雙方嘅部門咧，佢冇一啲嘅協作同埋配合嘅時候咧，其實係好難令到佢哋去離開呢個家暴。
私部嘅環境或者係性暴嘅環境啦，咁呢啲少數婦嘅婦女咧，喺普遍佢哋都係缺乏咗，無論係加成性暴力嘅人咧，佢哋都缺乏咗權益嘅認知啦。咁而由於咧翻譯嘅質素係唔足夠，引致到咧佢哋去誒報警嘅時候，或者甚至上堂作工嘅時候咧，都造成。
好多唔公義嘅地方，例如咧喺翻譯員咧就會將好多個人嘅價值觀加諸喺受害人身上啦，叫佢哋唔好報警啦，甚至出現咧喺法庭上面都出現一啲翻譯出錯嘅情況。咁而家我哋知道指引涵蓋嘅範圍嘅廿三個政府部門入邊咧，其實都涉及好多唔同嘅部門。咁其實無論譬如寫。
處啊、警處啊、醫院啊、律政處等噉，但係政府部門即係喺呢一方面，其實誒，我哋都睇到好多前線童工係冇接受一啲文化同埋性別敏感嘅培訓。咁期望我哋期望咧，即係指引可以review下，即係呢啲嘅即係情況啦，係令到一啲嘅翻譯人員啦，或者前線童工咧，係提供畀佢。
提供佢哋有關文化同埋性別敏感嘅訓練課程啦，以至到咧係提高佢哋嘅質素嘅。咁時間關係，我就即係講到咁多。好唔該曬誒，我哋如果在席嘅委員冇反對嘅話，我哋將個會議再延長少時間。我咁初步去到十五分鐘先好嘛。唔好意思，各位政府嘅代表同埋各位出席嘅人士，因為我哋嘅時間上啲，而且個比較係啊緊迫一少少。
誒，我哋先聽埋兩位其他在席嘅朋友嘅發言先。誒，陳維威先生唔該。誒，多謝主持。誒，咁都好多謝，即係今日今日咁多位小數作為，即係誒為咗自己權利去發聲先啦。咁誒，第二就係咧，即係都想講一講一個好重要問題，就係即係喺呢個會議之前咧，我咪兩點鐘咧就即係我哋上文年就去咗呢一個嘅長沙灣政。
法務處抗議學資處拖延學童嘅新，即係嗰個學費嘅津貼噉樣啦，即係其中有啲嘅情況係拖延咗幾個月，即係不斷收到幼稚園誒，即係畀佢嘅信就係話你再唔交學費咧，就即係我就會停止你個學童嘅學籍噉樣啦。即係個非常嚴重，其實我哋幾個月前都去過一次啦，即係去過一次抗議啊。嗰陣時我之
處即係有個人就話：，唉，我我即刻處理㗎啦！我哋慢咗，我哋即刻處理。去到今日都未處理好，即係佢哋就嚟畀人哋退學啦，係咪？即係誒一個月二千八百蚊嘅學費，即係對呢一班嘅誒難民嘅家庭嚟講咧，其實係真係你唔畀呢啲津貼，佢就畀唔到嗰個學費㗎啦。咁誒，其實即係我我會見到呢件事上面政府係絕對特別係即係學。
支持係絕對有責任去到盡快批咗嗰啲，即係誒學費津貼畀一班嘅難民家庭先啦。即係因為一次違反曬即係兒童權利國際公約幾條啊，大佬即係誒誒兒童權利國際公約第廿六條就話，締約國應該咧確認每個學兒童係有權受益於社會保障，但係即係你依家噉樣喺度拖延學童嘅呢啲學費。
津貼，即係令到佢哋讀唔到書係非常嚴重嘅問題。第二就係咧，即係廿七條嘅誒廿八條一咧，就話替約國確認兒童有受受教育嘅權利啊。為喺機會均等嘅基礎上逐步實現此項權利，誒替約國係應該要即係去以一切適用嘅方式，令到佢哋有受誒教育嘅即係機會。
資源去幫助呢一啲學生。
silence is worse than refusal.
exempted that sort of revamp, right? There's no such government refusal. That's it. Not yet, anyone.係嘛？係石禮謨。
亦都希望官員知道啊！佢哋做咁多嘢，出咁耐、咁延長嘅會議，都係只係想好似我哋噉樣啫。其實有啲咩要求咧？有啲咩奢望咧？我真係想補充你一點，多謝主席。好啊。
唔該，周生。誒，時間關係咧，我哋有三位委員咧就初步顯示咗有需要發言嘅，或者大家如果唔介意嘅話，我哋將個時間收輕輕少少。有冇冇患症議員就放棄咗發言啊？其他兩位同事咧，有乜好發言咧？係，或者。
噉樣即係其實學資取，我諗噉樣咧，即係你你係幾個月都唔畀啲學費啲人，即係你一方面又唔畀呢一班嘅難民去打工，另外一方面你又唔批啲，盡快批啲學費畀佢哋，即係即係佢哋點樣讀書。第二就係仲有非常多誒學校嘅一啲使費係需要用嘅，即係你噉樣係其實我覺得係打壓緊佢哋嘅受教育嘅機會，即係呢個非常嚴重嘅問題。
希望即係政府盡快去處理呢個問題。第二就係即係其實原本係想用多啲時間去講即係外傭佢哋喺香港面對嘅歧視，但係即係剛剛喺誒等緊嘅時候，我聽到即係有民建聯嘅蔣麗雲員就話：，唉，我哋民建聯又幫即係誒一班小組做咗呢樣，做咗嗰樣。喂，但係我真係唔該諗清楚，即係興非常興，你一方面喺度話即係要。
講難民嘅問題，你不斷喺話啲難民係假難民，講緊啲乜嘢？即係其實我承認，即係政府喺處理難民嘅學型申請上面，即係非常慢。九即係一五年嘅數據係九千八百八十四宗要處理五年到啦，大概係噉。你喺呢五年嘅時間，你處理緊學型申請，你話啲人係假難民。第二就係即係我試過喺深，因為我之前住深水埗。
即係好多，其實佢佢已經係香港居民嘅一啲，即係外籍人士、黑人噉樣啦。佢試過係即係翻工去見工嘅時候，畀人話：，唉，啲老細見到佢話，喂，你咪搞下民眾打工，我哋唔請嘅，唔請嘅。即係你呢啲係完全，即係如果我我會認為民建聯啊、蔣麗雲呢啲人咧，喺度鼓吹緊呢度叫種族中傷啊，即係佢哋佢哋喺玩畀個社會。
會知道餵你呢啲所有嘅同我哋睇落膚色唔同嘅咧，都會係難民嚟嘅，都係一啲假難民啦，或者係即係你喺度鼓吹呢啲噉樣嘅信息，真係非常嚴重。唔該，如果政府係正視種族平等的問題，唔該係要做翻啲嘢，即係特別係蔣麗雲啊、民建聯呢一堆噉樣嘅人咧，真係唔該盡快正視呢個問題處理下佢哋啊。唔該，陳生，跟住我哋有請。
啊，係今日咧，誒見翻啊謝偉俊先生喺度主持一個噉嘅會議咧，講促進呢一個種族平等行政指引咧，我係百感交集嘅。二零一一年咧，謝偉俊先生就大力反對外傭居港權啦。噉啊喺香港辛勤服務香港人家庭七年，就算做足七十年嘅外籍家務工咧。
佢都話應該係冇居港權嘅噉就誒。如果呢個議會議員係咁關心種族平等嘅話咧，噉我希望咧就誒多啲去關心下外傭嘅權益，因為外外籍家務工依然係面對好多歧視性嘅政策嘅。咁當年咧就誒我咧同埋一啲朋。
朋友咧，噉啊去追擊謝偉俊反外容居港權嘅街站啊，咁同埋一啲嘅遊行啦，噉啊最尾咧，我哋都一堆人被捕，最後就有五個人被定罪嘅嚇。噉啊呢呢一筆啊，下次真係講外容我再講。噉啊今次呢一個小組委員會嘅討論文件咧，就係講呢一個速。
進種族平等行政指引嘅落實情況，噉啊內容基本上主要都係講增加嗰啲不同語言嘅廣播啊、單張啊噉樣。咁呢一啲嘢如果可以做多啲咧，絕對係好嘅。但係更加緊要嘅係自細畀佢哋更加多教育方面嘅支援，噉樣佢哋先至有機會咧去尋求一個更加。
合理嘅生活噉。之前喺海麗村嘅罷工咧，社民連左翼廿一同埋其他團體都有去幫手嘅。噉啊喺我哋派單張嘅過程裏邊咧，就見到好多少數族裔嘅細路仔咧，佢哋零零舍舍係肯喺度聽下發生咩事啊，肯去攞單張睇啊。噉我哋叫佢哋不如攞啲畀你啲朋
有睇啦，佢哋又好肯誒話誒攞啲單張畀朋友噉。但係即係當我去問佢哋，你哋睇唔睇得明啲單張啊？噉啊，答案啊好傷感嘅。佢哋咁關心其他嘅人，但係佢嗰啲單張佢哋只係睇得明少少嘅啫。佢哋話即係佢哋讀緊一般嘅小學，又或者好似頭先嗰位朋友所講，佢哋。
誒，就算讀到大學都好咧，佢哋嘅中文水平咧，往往都係即係誒比較低嘅。咁呢個對於佢哋融入香港嘅社會係好好辛苦啊。咁同埋而家越嚟越多學校咧係用普教中嘅，用普通話去教中文。咁即係講開廣東話嘅學生咧，面對普教中都咁痛苦嘅時候。
呢一啲小數族裔，佢哋面對普教中嘅話，佢哋冇可能適應得到。咁當然學校未必掟佢哋去普通話班，但係佢哋可以有嘅選擇咧就少好多。又或者係而家咧，其實都仲有一啲嘅幼稚園咧，面試嘅時候係一定係要用廣東話或者普通話去答問題嘅。
咁誒，而家教育局咧就有按呢一個學校錄取嘅非華語學生數目去提供額外撥款。噉我哋希望咧呢一方面嘅撥款咧係可以再增加，噉啊去提高咧學校收取非華語學生嘅誘因，同埋令到肯收呢一啲學生嘅學校咧能夠有更加多嘅。
係。
誒。
咁又點咧？
有冇投訴機制咧？
如果去投訴嘅話，向邊個投訴咧？
講指引啦，但係我想問咧，如果呢廿幾個政府部門唔跟個指引？
嗰時有都唔知嘅噉，咁呢啲有冇實際解決方法咧？噉，噉我哋都會好好好好實在去睇呢啲嚇。
嘅，啊！我哋翻去睇睇每個部門喺呢一方面遇到啲咩實際困難，嚇有冇解決方案？噉就呢個係我哋今年嚇希望檢討嘅一個重點啦。
好啦，誒，亦都想一並回應，就係支持。遵守指引嘅後果咧，局長或者你係啦係啦，呢呢個呢個好清晰嘅，誒，嗰個行政指引咧係政府即係最高層通過嘅一個，所有部門都要跟隨嘅指引。
我哋講講幾講嘅，好嚇歡迎嚇誒，或者邵家章議員先好嘛？多謝主席。誒，我原本咧有有啲問題係圍繞住誒收集數據啊。而家佢過往唔收集數據，點樣去定政策呢啲問題，或者我有啲問題係圍繞住指引係指引唔到政府部門嚇，所以要強化指引或者強化力度嘅問題。不過我呢啲都。
今日咧啲時間好好過曬時，我唔講啦。我即係想最尾咧，我想特別要多謝呢位呢位朋友。佢嗰句好似你哋噉樣，佢只係想我哋只係想好似你哋噉樣。佢講咗三次好似你哋噉樣呢句，我覺得啲説話其實誒真係好入心入肺啊！多謝你啊！如果希望，
Just one line. I want to put on the record that the government has not refused to look into the racial bias ordinance. Blah blah. That the government's powers and functions should no longer be.
It's also on record， so don't worry about it。張志紅議員唔該。係好，誒今日咧，我哋個議題，當然多謝好多團體嚟到，我哋亦都係誒非常之贊成好多今日出席，尤其是你講翻你個人經驗嘅誒呢啲少數族裔嘅朋友。誒今日我哋。
呢個指引係內地內誒政制及內地事務局發出嘅，咁邊一個負責監察呢個指引咧？頭先啊副局長講一大餐冇答我呢個問題。好啊，不仲有少少時間容許我哋要求或者邀請局長答答呢個問題。再如果有其他需要補充嘅，書面上可以答。石一如你想發言啊？
我我唔係發言，我想只係頭先嗰位，好似我上一上一屆上一次嗰啲朋友講咗好多好好嘅意見。我好希望政府咧答翻佢哋呢件，好似今次咁喺誒書面答翻我哋佢啲意見，因為今日冇可能答到嘅，主席。好，我相信在座嘅官員聽到曬你大家委員嘅。
意見或者我用啲少時間畀局長就剛才嗰個所謂指引，如果唔遵守嘅話，有咩後果喺度咧？先作咗回應。主席，你可能畀幾分鐘我，因為咁多有心人講咗咁多嘢，我都想即係重點回應。啊，好快啊！第一就係部門數目點解廿三個而唔係全部嗱廿三個係目前嘅進度。
個個唔係終點，It's not the end。啊，We will ask more departments to join。啊，Progress is make。We are making good progress， and we continue to make more progress。我哋其實誒每年都希望多啲部門參與嘅。最初咧係只係得十。
十四個啊，逐漸加超一半，去到廿三個噉。我哋嘅目標係越多越好嘅啊。咁一路會去爭取多啲部門加誒。第二咧就係呢個環節咧都係啊，一路聚焦兩點啦。第一就係數據嗰個蒐集統計數據呢一點，我哋冇疑議。
聚焦聚焦，講講個教育問題，所以特別好多問題關於教育嘅咧，我哋都可以由下次再處理嘅，好嘛？噉就誒時間關係咧，我諗我哋要結束呢個會議。再一次咧，就誒講聲對唔住，因為我哋今日安排上咧啲而且個比較長，少少特別在座嘅政府同事們同埋出席嘅公眾人士們，非常感激你哋出席嘅，多謝曬大家，多謝。
誒翻譯服務睇到就係話啊，其實會唔會每個部門可以做得貼身一啲？聽到就係話有啲部門嘅誒誒，根本係或者用嗰啲部門嘅服務嘅市民少數聚嘅朋友，其實都唔知有翻譯服務嘅嚇。呢個譬如呢度連連個。
噉你承諾得跟咧，你就跟㗎啦。如果唔跟嘅話咧，就同一般嘅行政失當無異嘅嚇。咁譬如誒，申訴專員係可以處理呢個申投訴嘅。噉就暫時答唔到嘅，或者我哋希望下一次有機會書面再再跟進啦。而家我哋下一次開會嘅時間咧，都會再聚。